<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Moses returned from Midian; or, Gods kindnesse to a banished king his office, and his subjects duty. As it was delivered in a sermon, preached at Linlithgow, on the day of thanksgiving for His Majestie our Soveraigns happy restauration. By J.R. M.L. and published by A.G. P.L. Published by authority.</title>
            <author>Ramsey, James.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57856</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R222</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217055</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828756</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828756</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33187</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57856)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33187)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1958:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Moses returned from Midian; or, Gods kindnesse to a banished king his office, and his subjects duty. As it was delivered in a sermon, preached at Linlithgow, on the day of thanksgiving for His Majestie our Soveraigns happy restauration. By J.R. M.L. and published by A.G. P.L. Published by authority.</title>
                  <author>Ramsey, James.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Gedeon Lithgow,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>J.R. = James Ramsay.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33187:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MOSES Returned from MIDIAN; OR, Gods kindneſſe to a Baniſhed KING; His Office, and His Subjects duty.</p>
            <p>As it was delivered in a SERMON, Preached at <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lithgow,</hi> on the day of Thankſgiving for His MAJESTIE our Soveraigns Happy Reſtauration.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. R. M. L.</hi> And publiſhed By <hi>A. G. P. L.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ACTS 7.34.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>I have ſeen, I have ſeen the affliction of My People which is in Egypt, and I have heard their groa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and am come down to deliver them: and now, come, I will ſend thee into Egypt.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Magiſtratus eſt res optima &amp; feraciſsima multorum bonorum operum.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Bull. Dec 2. Ser. 6.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Principio, ſubditorum eſt, ſanctè, reverenter &amp; honorificè, non abjectè &amp; vulgariter, ſentire de Principibus ſuis.</p>
               <p>Exhibeant eis etiam (ſubditi) foris honorem, cuique regno &amp; patriae conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum. Idem.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Dec. 2. Ser. 9.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Printed by <hi>Gedeon Lithgow.</hi> 1660.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:33187:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33187:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:33187:3"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:33187:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>MOSES</hi> returned from <hi>MIDIAN:</hi> OR, Gods kindneſs to a Baniſhed KING; His Office, and His Subjects duty.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ACTS 7.35.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>This <hi>Moſes</hi> whom they refuſed, ſaying, Who made thee a Ruler and a Iudge? The ſame did God ſend to be a Ruler and a Deliverer, by the hands of the Angel which appeared to him in the Buſh.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Overnment is ſo neceſſary for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment of an orderly and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable ſociety amongſt men, that, next to the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, there is no greater bleſſing can be beſtowed by the Lord upon a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple then a lawfull and righteous <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,</hi> who will govern for the Lord, ruling in righteouſneſſe and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Therefore doth this Proto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>martyre <hi>Steven,</hi> while he is recoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the great mercies of God to the Church of the Jews, ſtay long in rehearſing the Lords ſending of <hi>Moſes</hi> to be Ruler, &amp;c. unto them, as the Churches eminent mercie; yea, in all this recapitulation, he mentioneth none of the ſins of the Jews, but
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33187:4"/>that of rejecting <hi>Moſes</hi> their Ruler, verſ. 27. and 39. and their black ſin of Idolatrie, which (verſ. 40.) followed upon their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting of <hi>Moſes:</hi> That we might ſee, that Rebellion againſt lawfull Authoritie, is as unavoidably the forerunner of rejecting God, as honour to the King, is, by the Apoſtle, (1 <hi>Peter</hi> 2.17.) immediatly ſubjoyn'd to the fear of God.</p>
            <p>My Text ſeemeth to quadrat well with what is the occaſion of this joyfull Day: which will the better appear, by holding out the ſeverall parts and purpoſes therein contained. They are three: The firſt, is the ſinful and rebellious cariage of the people to a Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler ſent them of God, <hi>They refuſed,</hi> &amp;c. Secondly, What the righteous Lord, out of compaſſion to His people, did for this oppreſſed and refuſed Ruler or King (ſo the Spirit of God calls him, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.5.) <hi>God ſent him,</hi> &amp;c. Thirdly, You have a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold office, to the adminiſtration whereof, he is ſent and commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned of the Lord, <hi>viz. Ruler, Judge</hi> and <hi>Deliverer:</hi> Under which alſo relatively, the duety of people is determined and ſet within its limits. There is alſo a fourth thing in the words, <hi>viz.</hi> the hand by the which <hi>Moſes</hi> is ſent to that office: which, becauſe time will not allow us to ſpeak of, is purpoſely forborne in the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, The peoples ſinfull and rebellious cariage, in theſe words, <hi>They refuſed,</hi> or <hi>denyed,</hi> as the word is moſt ordinarily tranſlated; yea, the word is ſometimes uſed for a refuſall or a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyall with diſdain and undervaluing, as <hi>Acts</hi> 3.13. which alſo accompanied therefuſall in the words, as is clear from the diſdain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſaying attending it at the back in theſe words, <hi>Who made thee, &amp;e?</hi> ſuch an anſwer as we uſe to give to buſſie medlers in matters not belonging to them: And, verſ. 39. its ſaid, <hi>They thruſt him away, and would not obey him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond purpoſe in the text, is, what the King of Kings did for this refuſed and thruſt away Depute of His, concerning which, the text holdeth cut. Firſt, What the Lord did in the time of his exile; even kept fellowſhip with him, through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt the Angel that dwelt in the Buſh, comforting and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting him in a wonderfull manner, that he might know he was not rejected of God, though refuſed by men. Secondly, That God ſent him, after his long ſo journing, as it were renewing his Commiſſion, and making him ſucceſſefull with a mighty hand, in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33187:4"/>this laſt eſſay, ſo that without violence the people are conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a ſubmiſſion unto him.</p>
            <p>The third purpoſe in the text, (as I have ſaid) is the parts of that office, to the exerciſe whereof he is ſent, <hi>viz. Ruler, Judge.</hi> and <hi>Deliverer:</hi> under which I conceive is comprehended all that a Soveraign can or ought to claim, and no more then ſhould be granted to him, ſince theſe three are expreſly in his Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from God, whoſe the Kingdom is; to the exerciſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, <hi>Moſes</hi> was brought by the hand of Jeſus Chriſt, the King of His Church, upon whoſe ſhoulders the Government lyeth: So that the conceding theſe things to the Ruler ſo ſent, can be no Dammage, but rather advantage, to the Church of Chriſt. But what each of theſe comprehendeth of the Rulers power, ſhall be ſhewed afterward.</p>
            <p>Now it followeth that we proceed to the <hi>Doctrines:</hi> and in the entrie I would warn you, that this text, being ſo full of weighty matter, it will not be poſſible, in the ſhort time allowed us, to preſſe forth the whole ſubſtance thereof; nor muſt that requiſite acuracie, in ſuch points, be expected from me. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore many <hi>Doctrines</hi> I muſt paſſe altogether: and ſuch as ſhall be named, muſt be diſcharged with greater brevitie then per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the matter would require. But, to proceed, I make the firſt Doctrine to be,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That Government, is, in it ſelf, a thing ſo evidently neceſſary and uſefull, that even the oppoſers of lawfull Governours, will not speak againſt Government.</hi> This is grounded upon theſe words, <hi>This</hi> Moſes, <hi>whom they refuſed.</hi> Where it's only the perſon which they queſtion; and afterwards, <hi>Who made thee,</hi> &amp;c? Wherein they challenge nothing but his Warrand, Commiſſion, and Authority for exerciſing of that Office. See alſo verſ. 27. It will be ſupperfluous labour to prove the truth of this <hi>Doctrine,</hi> The neceſſity and uſefulneſſe of Government being clear from <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.14. Where, to be without a Ruler, is to be as the Fiſhes of the ſea and the creeping things, the weaker whereof, are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by the greater and mightier; as alſo from that <hi>Judg.</hi> 17. 6. Where it's ſaid, that <hi>in the dayes</hi> wherein <hi>there was no King in Iſrael, every man did that which was right in his own eyes:</hi> Which is alſo repeated, chap. 18. verſe 1. and 19.1. and chap. 21. verſ. 25. In which places, it is alſo obſervable, that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33187:5"/>there is mention made of the wrong which the <hi>Levites</hi> (the Church-men) ſuſtained, that thereby we might ſee how uſefull, even to the Church, a right conſtitution of Civil Government is. Without this the Church wants the benefit of that promiſe, (<hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.23.) that <hi>Kings ſhould be nurſing fathers;</hi> yea, (<hi>Hoſ.</hi> 3.4.) to be without a King, and to be without a Sacrifice do go together. The Church may be perſecuted by wicked Rulers, but ordinarily is not taken away, and wholly rooted out, but by the rooting out of the eſtabliſhed Government of that Nation wherein the Church is. And have we not ſeen how the Church was wronged among us by the boundleſs toleration of errour, the Government and Judicatories thereof encroached upon by Acts and Ordinances, taking the power of Plantations out of the hands of eſtabliſhed Judicatories, and putting the ſame in the hands of others not concerned, and ſeverall ſuch other practices, as might be inſtanced, ever ſince the violence was done to the ſettled Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Government of theſe Kingdoms? from theſe things we may ſee how uſeful civil Government is, not only for the State, but for the Church alſo. Therefore, as we ought to bewaile the ſad ſufferings of our King, and ſeriouſly mourn before the Lord for theſe ſins, that provocked his Holineſſe to make our <hi>Iſrael</hi> be ſo many dayes without a King; So it is our duty, to praiſe and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the Lord, who hath graciouſly returned to us our ancient and known Government, and our own King, to exerciſe the ſame: whereby we have a full accompliſhment of that promiſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.26. <hi>I will reſtore thy Judges as at the firſt, and thy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours as at the beginning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond <hi>Doct.</hi> is, <hi>That even a righteous and good King, may be thruſt away, and refuſed by theſe over whom he is ſent of God to Govern.</hi> This ſo clearly ariſeth from what is in the text, that we need not ſtand to clear the ground. See alſo verſ. 27. and 39. The ſame was <hi>Davids</hi> caſe, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. and 5. chap. And for the proſecution of this point, I judge it not unfit to take a ſhort view of theſe few things, which concurred in the thruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Moſes</hi> away: As firſt, Who the perſon was, that refuſed and thruſt him away; and he is deſcribed, ver. 27. to be one, <hi>that did the other wrong,</hi> that is, a violent and wicked oppreſſour of his brethren. Secondly, What it was that moved this op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſour to thruſt <hi>Moſes</hi> away; even fear of puniſhment: he had
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33187:5"/>done evil, and feared the Judge, <hi>Thinks thou to kill me?</hi> He deſired, in effect, to be Judge himſelf, and could not endure any above him to controul his dealing with the weaker: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, would not ſo much as ſuffer <hi>Moſes</hi> to be an amicable advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, ver. 26. much leſſe to be Judge, ver. 27. Thirdly, The means whereby this rebellion is carried on: and they are three. 1. The calling in queſtion and contemning of his Authority and Warrantableneſſe of his undertaking, <hi>Who made thee a Ruler,</hi> &amp;c? 2. Reproaches of him as a bloody man, that would kill all he ruled over, though he had no other ground, but his own prejudged opinion, miſrepreſenting <hi>Moſes</hi> for one act of Juſtice, in killing the <hi>Egyptian:</hi> Wherein, though hee ſpeak the truth materially; yet it was <hi>malo animo,</hi> to bring <hi>Moſes</hi> in hazard. 3. The third mean, whereby this rebellion was carried on to it's hight, was violence, <hi>he thruſt him away,</hi> ver. 27. And where the Authority of a Ruler begins to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned, there (if it be in the contemners power) thruſting away cometh in the cloſe: The fourth thing conſiderable in the thruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Moſes</hi> away, is the grounds upon which this refuſing and rebellion is builded: and we find no real ground of provocation from <hi>Moſes,</hi> his worſt word we find (ver. 26.) to be, <hi>Sirs, ye are Brethren, why do ye wrong one to another?</hi> Innocencie in a King, will not reſtrain rebellious Subjects. Fifthly, Conſider what are the ſad effects of a rebellion, (coming to it's hight) even upon the Subjects, to wit, oppreſſion of the weaker by the ſtronger. See <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3.2, 3, 4, 5. And laſtly, That rebellion, once coming the length of thruſting away, God muſt, in a more then ordinary way, interpoſe for the reintroducing of the expulſed Ruler.</p>
            <p>I ſhall ſay no more for the application of this point, But that the ſin of theſe who had hand in the horrid murther of our late Soveraign, or the expulſion of our preſent, is more inexcuſable then that of this oppreſſing Iſraelite, who thurſt <hi>Moſes</hi> away, becauſe their juſt tittle to the Government, was more evident to them then <hi>Moſes</hi> tittle at that time was to the Jews. And therefore we ought earneſtly to ſupplicat the throne of grace, that theſe ſins may no more be laid to the charge of theſe Lands; and that the diviſions of the people, may be ſolidly healed: for it is marked, as the firſt riſe of the occaſion of this rebellion againſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> that <hi>the people ſtrove,</hi> v. 26.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:33187:6"/>
            <p>We might gather our third <hi>Doct.</hi> by comparing this verſ. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their refuſall of <hi>Moſes</hi> is ſpoken of, with verſ. 30. Where his fourty years ſojourning, in a exiled condition, is mentioned, to be, <hi>That ſinfull oppoſition and thruſting away of a righteous Ruler, may have ſucceſſe for along time; but the ſucceſſe of the oppreſsour, is the ſervitude of the ſubjects.</hi> I will not ſtand on this <hi>Doct.</hi> It is too ſad a Theme to inſiſt upon. Only this, Although we have reaſon to lament, that by the ſucceſſe of oppreſſours our King hath been ſo long kept away from us; yet, we have alſo reaſon to bleſſe God, that it hath not been for full fourty years; and to praiſe Him from our ſouls, who hath ſaid concerning us as he ſaid concerning the Jews, verſ. 34. <hi>I have ſeen, I have ſeen the affliction of my people, I have heard their groaning, and am come down to deliver them: and now, come, I will ſend thee into Egypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth <hi>Doct.</hi> aryſing clearly from the words, is, <hi>That though a righteous Ruler be thurſt away, and long kept away from his juſt right; Yet the Lord can, in his time, ſend him back to the exerciſe of that Government he had right to.</hi> So dealt the Lord with <hi>David,</hi> both after <hi>Sheba's</hi> rebellion and <hi>Abſolom's;</hi> And ſo hath the Lord done to our King; and it will not be amiſſe here to conſider a little ſome things, wherein the ſufferings and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of our King, is parallel to the ſufferings and the return of <hi>Moſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt, their ſufferings, after their expulſion, are parallel: Firſt, In that both their rights was unqueſtionable before God and man, though they wanted the exerciſe. Secondly, both driven to exile, and put to great pinches under it. Thirdly, made to ſojourn among people of another Religion. Fourthly, Yet both remained conſtant in the Truth, (the great glory of their ſufferings,) notwithſtanding of their ſtrong temptations. Fifthly, Both found more relief of ſtrangers then of friends. Sixthly, Both waited patiently untill Gods time of outgate came.</p>
            <p>There are alſo ſome things, wherein the manner of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning is parallel, as, Firſt, Gods hand was eminently ſeen in both. Secondly, their return was without blood, or War. Thirdly, Both were unexpected. Fourthly, both were, when the affliction of their people was at a great hight.</p>
            <p>Let us then bleſſe and praiſe the mighty Lord, whoſe right hand hath done marvellouſly. This day is ſet a part for this end: O
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33187:6"/>let praiſe be rendred, and our vows which were made, when our harps did hing on the Willows, be this day payed in the ſight of all the people; the Lords doing in this, is not after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of man. Look to what he hath done in reſtoring the breath of three languiſhing Kingdoms; look how mercifully he hath done it, and how unworthy we were, that our Poſterity, much leſſe our ſelves ſhould have ſeen it, and all cryes aloud, that it is our duty ever to praiſe Him, and not to let this ſo great a bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit ſlip out of our minde. Yea, with our praiſe, let us joyn prayer, that God may make our King, who hath been in ſo many things like to <hi>Moſes</hi> in his ſufferings and return, like to him alſo in the ſequell of his Reign, both for gracious and royall enduments, and beyond him for length of dayes; Yea, let us pray, God would make him according to his own heart: And we may have the greater encouragement in this, from what the Lord hath done for Him, and made appear in Him; As alſo, that moſt ordinarily, the beſt Kings, regiſtrat in Scripture, were ſuch as the Lord trained in the ſchool of affliction, as may be ſeen in <hi>Moſes, David, Jehoaſh,</hi> and many others mentioned, both in Sacred and Profane Hiſtorie.</p>
            <p>The fifth and laſt <hi>Doct.</hi> that I ſhall name, is this, <hi>That whom God ſends to the government of a people, he alſo giveth them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion for the Dignities, Authority, and power belonging to their place:</hi> for, ſaith the text, <hi>He ſent Moſes to be Ruler and Deliverer;</hi> Not to be one of the Rulers and Deliverers, which would take in others to a parity with him, but to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (that is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: And although that this ſame God, that ſent him, doth limit him and all Soveraigns, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.14. Yet, he takes nothing from them eſſentiall to Soveraignty. So when he ſends Apoſtles, Miniſters, &amp;c. all belonging to their office is allowed them, and ought not to be encroached upon; for, we can no more expect the full and free exerciſe of any office from one who is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained therein, then a free flight from the pinioned bird; take away the leaſt lith that God hath framed Soveraignty with, and the Soveraign is pinioned. But for the more orderly and full ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of this <hi>Doctrine,</hi> there are theſe four things to be a little opened up. Firſt, Something concerning a Monarchs Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or the fountain whence he derives his Authority. Secondly, Somewhat of his Prerogative and eminent Power. Thirdly,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33187:7"/>Somewhat of his office, and the duty he is bound before God to perform in the behalf of his people. Fourthly, Somewhat of the peoples duty, which relatively they are bound to perform to him.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt of theſe, to wit, the Soveraigns Commiſſion, wee ſee it is from God, <hi>God ſent him,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, The word uſed in the Miſſion of the Apoſtles. Whence we infer: Firſt. That a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Soveraign, hes his Authority immediatly from God (<hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1.) and not from the people, who, being of God appointed to be ſubject to Rule, and ruled, can have no power of ruling in themſelves, there being as clear diſtinction betwixt the Ruled and Ruler, as is betwixt the <hi>relatum</hi> and <hi>correlatum</hi> of any other relation: wherefore there are ſome Kings, who take their ſword from off an Altar, in token of their receiving their power imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly from God; ſo that the aſſertion, which alloweth to people a <hi>Majeſtas realis,</hi> ſeemeth to be groundleſſe, and diſhonourable to God the only Original and Fountain of Soveraignity; As alſo becauſe it takes away the diſtinction betwixt <hi>Governour</hi> and <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned.</hi> Secondly, I infer as following on the former, that a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, having his Commiſſion from God, as is ſaid, (though God will call him to an account) yet he is countable to none elſe for his adminiſtration but to God only: Not only becauſe he hath no <hi>Pares</hi> to be his Judge; But, becauſe no Commiſſioner is anſwerable to any Authority, but that which did cloath him with the Commiſſion, and that is (upon this ſubject) God who hath ſaid, <hi>By me Kings reign, Prov.</hi> 8.15, 16. Thirdly, I infer, that Soveraigus may expect Gods preſence and aſſiſtance in the work of their office, if they look to and depend upon him from whom they have their Commiſſion. Fourthly, I infer, that the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and reſiſting of them, is to reſiſt the Authority of God from whom they have their Commiſſion.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, The words hold out ſomething of his Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and eminent Authority, as neceſſarily annexed to his Office and place, to the which his Commiſſion bears him, in theſe words, <hi>God ſent him to be Ruler and Deliverer.</hi> Where it is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable, that what <hi>Steven</hi> calleth a <hi>Ruler,</hi> is in <hi>Exod.</hi> 2.14. cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a <hi>Prince:</hi> to ſhew, that all the prerogatives of Ruling, do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertain to a Prince. There are two words uſed in the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to wit, <hi>Ruler,</hi> and <hi>Deliverer,</hi> as ſaid is, under which the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33187:7"/>Soveraigns power, both in Peace and War, in Civil and Military affairs, is comprehended; as alſo, ſomewhat of that power, which is diſtinguiſhed <hi>in poteſtas Legibus aſtricta, &amp; Legibus ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luta:</hi> And under the firſt of theſe, <hi>viz. Ruler,</hi> is compryſed the power of <hi>Judging,</hi> which is mentioned in the beginning of the verſ. and adjoyned to <hi>Ruling,</hi> even by the rebel himſelf; Nor can it be denyed (I ſuppoſe) to appertain to the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Yea, ordinarly <hi>Ruling,</hi> and <hi>Delivering,</hi> are more controverted then <hi>Judging.</hi> But, to proceed, by the firſt, <hi>Ruler,</hi> there are theſe particulars of his Prerogative held forth unto us. Firſt, That he is Chief, Principall and Soveraign: therefore, even in contradiſtinction to all the people, he is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Which holds out a priority and preeminency in the perſon, beſide what it ſpeaks of his office. Secondly, That all authoritative Acts, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his Kingdoms, be in his name. Thirdly, That all Rule and Power in inferiour Officers, or Governours, be derived from him: Therefore the word ſignifies not only Authority; but a primary and fountain Authority. Fourthly, That he have the power of making the univerſall Laws of the Kingdom; for, theſe being the Rule both for inferiour Judges and the judged, it is requiſit, that the Ruler have a ſpeciall and Soveraign hand in making thereof, the Legiſlative power being naturally annexed to Soveraignity. Fifthly, That fince all power in inferiour Judges, is derived from him, their ſentence cannot be the laſt, but may be appealed from. Therefore the laſt appeall to any on earth is to the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, whoſe ſentence is finall and cannot be appealed from, but to God. Under theſe as the principall, are comprehended the power of diſpenſing with penall Laws by Pardons, and with po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive ſtatutes about duty by Licences; Yea, in ſome caſes, to alter and abrogat ſome Laws, although ordinarily, and without weighty cauſes theſe things are not to be done. Together with many other <hi>Jura majeſtatis</hi> reduceable to theſe and depending on the Soveraignity, as particularly, the making an univerſally ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidging interpretation of the Law, and the power of the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Law, without which, Soveraignity and Laws were but a mock-authority: Theſe two laſt, properly appertain to the tittle of the <hi>Judge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is moreover ſomewhat further of the Soveraigns pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, hold forth in the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſignifies <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33187:8"/>Saviour,</hi> as well as <hi>Deliverer;</hi> And this is his power in Military maters: which may be divided in theſe three: Firſt, His power to declare enemies to the State, the <hi>Deliverer</hi> being moſt oblidged and concerned, by vertue of his office, to know, and conſequently to judge and declare who are enemies. Secondly, His power of making Peace and War: For, he that may not command his Subjects to be in friendſhip, or to fight, doth but cary the empty tittle of <hi>Deliverer,</hi> and in vain expects obedience in Civils. Thirdly, His power of the Arms, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Strengths of his Kingdoms, both by Sea and Land, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing due to him for his and the Kingdoms ſecurity. As alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the governing of theſe things, is a principall part of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, experience having ſadly taught, that the power of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, not being ſubordinat to the Soveraign, uſurps a ſuperiority over him and the Kingdoms both; Yea, doth not reaſon teach, that a <hi>Deliverer</hi> ſhould not be without a ſword, nor have his ſword ſo lockt in the ſheath, that he cannot draw it till he call for the key from theſe who perhaps may refuſe it, and at length looſe it themſelves? take the ſword from the <hi>Deliverer,</hi> and quickly the Scepter ſhall be wrung from the <hi>Ruler.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I haſte to the third thing which I propoſed, <hi>viz.</hi> to hold out ſomewhat concerning the Soveraigns Office and Duty, which by vertue of this Commiſſion <hi>Moſes</hi> was, and all Soveraigns are oblidged to perform towards the people over whom God hath granted them to Rule: And this their Office may be ſummed up in this one, that he Rule for God, being faithfull to Him by whom Kings reign, and carefull of his peoples welfare. But we ſhall branch it out in theſe four: Firſt, that he be carefull of the welfare of the Church, the preciouſeſt intereſt that the King of Kings hath upon earth: This is a great part of his <hi>Ruling:</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. after that <hi>the reſtoring of Judges as at the firſt,</hi> and <hi>counſellours as at the beginning,</hi> is promiſed, v. 26. It is immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly ſubjoyned, v. 27. <hi>Zion ſhall be redeemed.</hi> And this is that which is promiſed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.23. and <hi>Kings ſhall be thy nurſing fathers.</hi> Under which theſe three are comprehended. Firſt, That he have a ſingular care that the purity of Doctrine be kept up, eſtabliſhed and maintained; errour and hereſie, with the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moters thereof, diſcountenanced and puniſhed, (not tolerated, which were unſuitable for the <hi>Defender of the Faith</hi>) according
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33187:8"/>to the example of good <hi>Joſiah,</hi> 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 34. throughout. Secondly, That the precious Ordinances of the Church, the Worſhip and Government thereof, be eſtabliſhed and defended by Law, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the example of <hi>Jehoſhaphat,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.8.11. As al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that the unity and concord of the Officers and Members there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of be tenderly kept up; and Rents or Schiſms ſolidly cemented. Thirdly, that the Liberties, Patrimony, and Maintenance of the Church be not encroached upon; But that faithful, learned and painfull Paſtours be encouraged, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 31.4. and their hands ſtrengthned by ſeconding the Cenſures of the Church by his Authority, and the concurrence of his inferiour Magiſtrates: All which are incumbent to him as a <hi>Ruler</hi> for God and a <hi>Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer</hi> from ſpirituall evills.</p>
            <p>The ſecond branch of the Soveraigns duty and office, is in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to morall tranſgreſſions, againſt which, Laws and Statutes ought to be made agreeable to the word of God; and theſe Laws would be impartially put in execution, without reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. Therefore, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.26. when <hi>Judges are reſtored as at the firſt,</hi> &amp;c. Then righteouſneſſe and faithfulneſſe ſpread in Burgh and Landwart. And v. 28. the puniſhment of the tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, of the ſinners and of them that forſake the Lord, is made mention of. This is no ſmall part of the righteouſneſſe whereby the throne is eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>The third branch of his Office, is in reference to the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Juſtice betwixt ſubject and ſubject: For which, not only wholſome and juſt Laws would be made for the good of the whole (and not for the advantage of ſome to the prejudice of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny;) But able faithfull and conſciencious men would be ſubſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, who, according to the juſt Laws, may impartially do ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to all.<note place="margin">2 Chron. 19 5.</note> This is his great duty as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a righter of the wronged, without which men would be but as the fiſhes of the ſea.</p>
            <p>The fourth and laſt branch of the Soveraigns duty and office towards his ſubjects, is in reference to their ſafety both by ſea and land, and their proſperity in their eſtates and callings: in order whereunto, he is called a <hi>Deliverer,</hi> watchfully to foreſee, and ſeaſonably prevent whatſoever may bring hazard and danger to them; or if they cannot be prevented, that then the ſubjects be as timely, tenderly and carefully delivered therefrom as is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33187:9"/>Thus <hi>Moſes</hi> delivered Iſrael from their bondage.</p>
            <p>There remaineth only the laſt thing to beſpoken to, to wit, the duty which the ſubjects are bound reciprocally to return to their Soveraign: And queſtionleſſe, the great weight of duty that lyes upon a faithfull Soveraign, calls for the loyall performance of all good Offices from the ſubjects to him. The Apoſtle, (1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.17.) ſummeth up all in one word, <hi>Honour the King:</hi> which may be branched forth in a fourfold duty, implyed in the tittles given in the text, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. <hi>Reverence,</hi> 2. <hi>Obedience,</hi> 3. <hi>Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> 4. <hi>Aid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay, our firſt duty is <hi>Reverence:</hi> and that, Firſt, of the mynd, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.20. <hi>Curſe not the King, no not in thy thought,</hi> or <hi>conſcience,</hi> as on the margent. They are called <hi>gods,</hi> and we ought as ſaith <hi>Bern. Sentire ſublimiter,</hi> have an high eſtimation of them. Secondly, <hi>Reverence</hi> in words, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.28. <hi>Thou ſhalt not revile the gods, nor curſe the Ruler of thy people:</hi> Which, (<hi>Acts.</hi> 23.5.) is tranſlated, <hi>Thou ſhalt not speak evill of,</hi> &amp;c. to ſpeak evill of them is to curſe them: And (<hi>Titus</hi> 3.2.) immediatly after the precept for ſubjection to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, there is a prohibition, <hi>Speak evill of no man:</hi> and as we ought to forbear every appearance of evill in other things; ſo eſpecially in this, the Authority of a Soveraign being very tender. Therefore, the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> in the forecited place of the <hi>Acts,</hi> maketh apology for calling the high Prieſt <hi>whited wall,</hi> although unjuſtly he had commanded him to be ſmitten: And <hi>Calvin</hi> on the place, ſaith in effect, that civil Authority is not to be ſhaken off though the Ruler were wicked. I find none in Scripture curſers of a King, but <hi>Shimei,</hi> and theſe <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.21. Where <hi>curſing of the King</hi> and <hi>of God</hi> are joyned together, <hi>They ſhall fret themſelves, and curſe their King and their God.</hi> Yea, by the Apoſtle we are commanded to pray for them; and at that time when he wrote, a wicked <hi>Nero</hi> reigned: The third kind of Reverence, is with the body, uſing a ſuteable geſture to regall Authority as the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of <hi>Tekoah,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam,</hi> 14.4: And <hi>Ahimaaz</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.28. So did all the people, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.20. I might multiply other citations, but it is ſuperfluous, <hi>exhibeant eis etiam foris honorem cuique regne &amp; pairia conſuetum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bullin: dec:</hi> 2. <hi>ſer:</hi> 9. ſpeaking of the duty of ſubjects to their Soveraign.</p>
            <p>The ſecond duty that we ow them, is <hi>Obedience,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13.14.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33187:9"/>
               <hi>Titus</hi> 3.1. Such <hi>Obedience</hi> it ought to be as excludeth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance to him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.2. As is willing, chearfull and for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.5. For, their Authority is an Ordinance of God, and they are the Miniſters of God; Yea, this <hi>Obedience</hi> is due from all perſons, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject,</hi> &amp;c. even Church-men as well as Laiks: for ſaith <hi>Bern.</hi> in one of his Epiſtles, writing to an Arch-biſhop, <hi>Quis vos excepit ex univerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate?</hi> It is true, that Kings have no power to exerciſe Miniſteriall acts themſelves; Yet they have power to put Miniſters to do that which they cannot do themſelves, and to puniſh them, when, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter orderly tryall, they are found guilty of Mal-adminiſtration: So <hi>David, Solomon, Jehoſhaphat, Hezekiah, Joſiah,</hi> &amp;c. governed the Prieſts, even as Prieſts, and the Levits as Levits: But, we ſay not, that Kings can puniſh Church-officers by any Eccleſiaſtick cenſure; they can no more depoſe then they can ordain: The power of neither of the keyes was given to Kings as Kings. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is this <hi>Obedience</hi> that we preſſe as due from all perſons, due in all things from any perſon: For, if Kings command what God forbids, Then the Apoſtles rule muſt ſtand, <hi>Acts.</hi> 5.29. <hi>Obey Gedrather then man.</hi> So did the Egyptian Midwives; So did the three children with approbation from God.</p>
            <p>The third duty we ow, is <hi>Fidelity:</hi> the breach whereof, is above diſobedience; <hi>Fidelity</hi> to his perſon, <hi>Fidelity</hi> to his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: if any of theſe be plotted againſt, or injured, there is <hi>laeſa Majeſtas.</hi> This made <hi>David</hi> ſay of <hi>Saul, God forbid I ſhould touch the Lords anoynted:</hi> Not a lap of his garment can be touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but the tender heart is ſmitten. And in Scripture, we find no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing taught for looſing ſubjects from their fidelity and alead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance. But on the contrary, the ſaints are recorded to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained loyall, even to wicked Kings and Emperours.</p>
            <p>The laſt duty is <hi>Aid:</hi> and that, Firſt, by ſaithfull counſell and advice, when called for; and diſcovery of his ſecret enemies and their plots. Secondly, by our eſtates, chearfully paying out thereof tribute and cuſtome, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.7. Chriſt himſelf payed pole-money, <hi>Match.</hi> 17.27. And, Thirdly, by our perſons: We ought to aſſiſt our Soveraign both againſt countrey Rebells and out-land Enemies, whenſoever it is called for by him, who hath it in his Commiſſion to be <hi>Deliverer:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have been the longer upon theſe things, becauſe no ſmall part
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:33187:10"/>of the dayes work is to teach you to give to God what is Gods due, even all Honour, Praiſe, Power and Dominion, being King of kings and the only Potentate, who hath made this day, that we may rejoyce therein: And to give to our <hi>Caſar</hi> what is his due, even <hi>Reverence, Obedience, Fidelity,</hi> and <hi>Aid:</hi> which is a debt upon us by Gods ordinance, and ought to be payed for conſcience ſake. I ſhall ſhut up all with repeating the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, <hi>Fear God, and honour the King.</hi> Theſe two are chain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together by the Holy Ghoſt: Who do the firſt, will not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect the laſt; and ſuch as are much taken up with the laſt, would not neglect the firſt: Go therefore, and through the reſt of this day, expreſſe your joy and thankfulneſſe, as the people did, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.22. When <hi>Solomon</hi> was made King the ſecond time, they did eat and drink (but it was before the Lord) on that day, with great gladneſſe. Beware of any exceſſe, Sin is no way to praiſe God, or pleaſe our good King who hath declared againſt it; Do, as, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.66. Pray for a bleſſing to the King, and go to your tents joyfull and glad of heart for all the goodneſſe that the Lord hath done for CHARLES our King, and <hi>Scotland, Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> His people. And thus, as we bleſſe God for him; So we pray for all bleſſings on him from the King im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall, inviſible and full of Glory, to whom be praiſe for now and ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
